I'm so excited to be here
I'm doing a little bit of nervousness right now
but I'm standing here today 23 years old
and I flew in the day before yesterday from Nepal
How does a 23yo american girl
from New Jersey college bound 4 years ago
end up in a remote himalayan village raising over 200
children who've been orphan as results of disease and civil war?
I'm here to tell you that story today
and I hope you enjoy it
The name of my project is Kopila Valley Children's Home
and just a couple of months actually we launched a school called Kopila Valley Primary School
My story began
exactly 5 years ago
when I woke up one morning at 18 years old
and I had a scary realization
I went to a great a public school in the US
I received what I think is one of the best educations our system has to offer,
but as much as I knew about
the outside world and all the facts that I've been forced to memorize
and retain on history and math,
I knew very little about myself and what I wanted in my life and the inside sort of things
and I was very lucky I woke up with that feeling at 18.
So I deferred college, I put off my university
for what I thought was going to be a year
and I packed up a backpack
with very few belongings and I decided to take a trip all around the world
I never really traveled, never left my country,
I've been on camping trips so I knew how to rough it
and packed everything I owned
as my friends where going off to their dorms
and set off to travel and hike and discover
I started off in the South Pacific Islands
and did volunteer work, conservation work
all of the sudden my whole world
opened up, there was so much to learn, so much to discover
outside of the 4 walls of a classroom
and I got my passion back, my passion to live,
to learn and to be human on this earth again
After that first couple of months
I realized I was hungry for more and I decided
to sign up for an internship in north eastern India
in a project for children
and I didn't know anything
it's good being young.
I just packed up my backpack again
got in an airplane and
set out for a foothill region in the north eastern India
and I was working with children
and it turned out that
where I happened to be volunteering and working
I was working with nepalese refugees,
a nepali refugee community
and as good my education was I didn't know
that Nepal was even a country
when I was 18 years old
I didn't know what was going on
I didn't know there've been a civil war
that forced children and families to flee their homes
and come to India, in this country that was still foreign to them
Picture your typical poverty
typical refugee community
living under plastic,
no water
menial jobs that even the untouchable indians won't do
and I started asking questions
if their living in these conditions that are so bad,
what they are running away from?
and it just so happened in 2006 that there was an armistice
and the border to Nepal opened up for the first time
and I became really curious and I wanted to take a trip,
so I packed my backpack again
and I decided with my good friend Sunita
Nepalese refugee, young girl, 16 years old
who'd left her village at about 8
and never returned
at the start of the Maoists insurgency
the two of us has become friends and
we're reading the happenings
and sort of trying to figure out what was going on in the country
And we decided to take a trip
and I had no idea what I was in for
I got in the bus
I was on that bus for 2 days
and then the driver sort of looked back at us
to these 2 young girls and he said
alright it's the end of the road it's time to get out
and sure enough we got out and ahead of us
was this himalayan stretch
of the most beautiful landscape I'd ever seen
and no road
and we got out and we had to trek for 2.5 days,
until we found Sunita's village
so I'm in a post-civil war
very ravaged, the war just ended
but just stunned by the beauty
and the sense of community and we trekked
I was the most sore I'd ever been, even as an athlete
but we made it
and the sad thing we discovered was that Sunita's home
and her family
had sort of disappeared
her village hut had been converted into the maoist military basecamp center
and her family wasn't there
again it was a meaningful trip
we got information on her family
and I felt this sense of belonging and this sense of home
that I hadn't felt in a very long time
and I knew there was something for me
so, my travels continued
and I ultimately ended up doing some city traveling
trek back down
and I was walking down the road one day
when I locked eyes with this little girl
her name's Lakoda
and I soon came to know that
this was her job, she is a child porter
and her job every day
was to take loads
this is about 60kg
from the bus park all the way into the villages
and she go back and forth, back and forth, all day
and as we know child labour
this is the reality of it
she make a $, $2 in the day
to feed her family
this is the life of a nepalese orphan
this is the life of an orphan child in our world today
I looked at her and I saw every single piece of myself
and I was devastated
I thought, what've we done as a human family
that our children are living this way?
I thought of myself, I saw every single piece of myself in this child
and I've thought, "oh God I grew up with a trampoline in my backyard
and I was in a soccer field, and I was going to my first dance when I was her age"
and my whole world just collapsed in a second
and I soon kept reading
and I found out there're 80 million children just like her in the world
and I was devastated, I was ashamed to be part of this human family
if this the way our children are living
I promise it get happier this story
so I continued to meet them, I was fascinated with these young girls
and there're stories of children on this side of this one particular riverbed
that I had to cross everyday to get to my room
where we were renting
and these girls would pick up dry rocks from the side of the riverbed
and break them into smaller pieces
and they'd sell them
and they were happy
believe it or not, there were smiles on their faces
and they made a life out of this for themselves
and then I met one particular girl,
her name was hima
this is hima here
she was 7yo
and she was one of those children on the side of the dry riverbed
but every day when I walked to meet her
she just smiled these big bright eyes
and she said "Namaste, Didi"
and someday she'd picking up garbage
but everyday was the same smile on the same look and it captured me
and I thought for the first time
"Ok, Maggie, forget the one million kids, forget the 80 millions"
I can't begin to wrap my fingers and my head around these stats
what if you just start with Hima
is there something that you can do to change the life of just one child
and I went around to the community, in the village
and I talked to principals, and village leaders, and the elders
and sure enough I found the reason why all these children where out of school
it was because they needed the income to support their families
and they couldn't afford the tuition fees, the uniform and the books
a pretty big chunk of money
which is about $8 to $10
and I thought at 18 and with the entrepreneurial mind that I have
ok I can do that
what if I just support the education of this one child
how'd her life change?
This is Hima a couple of weeks later
I put her into school
and followed and tracked her progress
and her life sure enough did change
if you know what happens when we educate young girls and women
the stats are unbelievable
it's not about it's just the right thing to do to put a child into primary school
the world will change when our children and our women are educated
they have less children
they raise better families, they raise more educated children
their diseases, everything decreases, poverty levels
communities and villages change
and the thing about this work that I do is that it's very addicting so I thought
ok, one kid. If I can do one, why not 10, why not 5?
what if my dream was walk across this dry riverbed one day and not see a single child breaking stone
that's what I want, I wanted create a world that I want to see every day
so these were the next 5 girls
that I enrolled into school.
but the sad thing was I didn't think was enough
there were kids that didn't have homes and families
they're orphans
one day I'd this idea
I found a piece of land
and it just happened to be $5000
I wanted to build a home for orphan kids, a home and a school and a base
the kids couldn't go to school 'cause they didn't have a home
they could call this place their home
I called my parents one day
and I said
can you send over my $5000 of lifesavings?
I saved that from the time I was about 6 years old, every penny
I babysat starting from the time I was 12 to when I was 18
and we had a very long conversation that day,
I think it was the middle of the night over there in the US
and sure enough because my parents are amazing people
they wired over that $5000 and I bought my first piece of property in Nepal
and I found this beautiful community of people and women and villagers and elders who wanted to help me
and wanted to support me and take part in this
we'd no money left after that, just a vision in this dream
and a couple of shovels
so all we did was take those shovels and dig a hole in the ground
that was all we could do
and I just had to get my hands dirty
and to be a part of it
I'd see everything that I wanted to create in my mind
but we didn't have the resources
we just had the sense of hope in that this was the right thing to do
this is one of the best days of my life
the whole village came out
and we dug the foundation to the home
every good home needs a solid foundation
I didn't have anything left except for a ticket home
so I went home and I started to babysit
I thought that I could babysit and nanny my way into building this home for children
and I got about 2 or 3 weeks in and I realized I have just enough money to build this septic tank
so I started to share my story with children and my community
and sure enough with garage sales and every fundraiser, big sales
you know, little, dollar at a time, we saved enough money to build this
and then the story broke in the newspaper "local girl's trying to build a home for children"
sure enough $20-$40 donations started coming in
and the home started going up
this is Cheran
my main mason, my hero
he build and helped with the design of the home
we had over 200 local people come out to take part in the construction
this is one of my favourites, Dev
and in just 6 months
we built this
it's a 2 storey home
that's now the home of 30 orphan children in Nepal
I got my first big break
to build the second storey, when I got a call from Cosmo Girl Magazine
they announced I was the winner of $20,000 from Maybelline, believe it or not.
I don't wear a lot of makeup
so that's pretty ironic
this girl on the phone calls up, she's in her 20s, she's very cosmopolitan New York city
"Guess what, I've the best news for you" and I'm like "What?!"
"You just won $20,000 from Maybelline
and I'm shocked, like my heart's speeding $20,000 is a ton of money over there
she goes: "It gets even better"
and I'm like: "What? What could possible better than $20,000 for my children
and she goes:
"We're gonna whisk you in NYC for a Maybelline makeover
and I thought "OK"
I had lice in my hair at that time
I still remember the hairdresser looking at me like:
"Oh my gosh, how did this girl get here"
but these are my children and this is where that $20,000 went
and the makeover was worth it. I didn't let them dye my hair chocolate brown
That was just somethings I wouldn't given to.
this is my family, I think this is when we're about 15
we've since grown to 30
Kopila is the home of children like Karma, she was sold at the age of 6 or 7 as a domestic servant
and her job was to take care of her of the younger children in this family
and every day she put their uniforms on and sent them off to school
and I've a clip of her expressing that sadness of sending the children off a path to school and not being able to go
she came down to live with us barefoot, she walked for 4 days to get from her village
and she did about 4 years worth of schooling in just one year, taught herself to read and write
we found her up in her bedroom writing the ABCs
this is my Nevine
it's amazing how these children take care of each other
they bring each other in
they just love one another so much
we can't even get them to sleep into separate beds
these are 3 of my girls
I could spend days telling you their stories
all of them would be the first literate generation of their families
the first girls and boys to get the chance to go to school
learn how to write their own name
we push sustainability: the children grown their own food their own vegetables
they're part of the cooking process
we raise goats and turkeys and chicken and cows
it's really an important part of what we do
especially in a country like Nepal where 90% of the population relies on subsistence farming
so we're trying to raise them with that awareness
I wish you could all come it's just this beautiful place, this beautiful slice of hope
Shortly after just last year, actually
I won a $100,000 from an organization called "DoSomething.org"
which was just a dream come true
things sort of just began to fall into place going from having no money
to all of a sudden having a $100,000 check in my hand
to do whatever I wanted
it was amazing
this is the night we found out we won the money
this is me with my parents
and without them, without their yes that they gave me to live my dream and follow my heart
this wouldn't be possible
so I wanted to put them in here
and with that $100,000, true to our American culture
I got my picture on the back of Doritos, America's favourite snack food
so if you're ever in the States pick them up it's the 'Cool Ranch' flavour
All of a sudden I had $100,000 in a year to build this school for 200 kids, over 200 children
at the same time this little boy was abandoned at the local bus station
and I found myself with a 1.5 year old
and he didn't have a name so
he had a scar on his forehead
and the kids named him Harry Potter
this is me with Harry
but we had to find a piece of land, right away
and I wanted to start, I wanted to get my hands dirty
the first I actually did with the money was take the kids on elephant rides
I decided for the architecture piece to go with bamboo
which if you can do some reading on bamboo constructions
it's sustainable, locally harvested, very strong, believe it or not, structurally
this is my son, Santo holding a piece
and sure enough people, the right people just started sort of show up
to help
I had an architect come over from Australia
Orr Niv, he left his high paid job, step out the office
heard of our story, and said "Hey, I'd come over and design this thing for you"
the cool thing about bamboo when you're on a low budget like I was
you can take it apart and put it back together
has a lifespan of about 20 years
it's like legos it's actually very fun to build with
but the local people didn't know how to use it and harvest it actually
so Orr did the job of really training the local team to build this by themselves
with their own resources and
he build this first classroom with them, this is the second grade
and he did the best thing he'd have done
he walked away, he went trekking for two weeks
and he said "alright guys, it's time for you to figure this out
and sure enough our local team that had never built
a bamboo construction built 3 more classrooms in the span of 2 weeks
this is our structure going up
this is the first 4 classrooms
nursery, the 2nd grade
that's the septic tank actually
the school has just opened this past june
and it's a beautiful place
it was made from the earth, with clay and stone
and bamboo and a tin roof
and the children, all 200 of them
will be again the first literate children of their families
they get health care
basic medical treatment
a meal every day
which is usually the only meal they'll receive
here's the aerial view from the house
the land that I ended up finding was just a stone throw away
after searching for six months and having deal after deal fall through
was not easy
this was a year of the hardest work that I ever done
and sleepless nights and everything else you can imagine
but that first day at school was amazing
we opened with a big puppet show
and we had this stage that we made
every psychologist that I've talked to
has said that for children the best you can do
is having them performing and doing arts and music and sports
just getting them to express themselves as much as possible
so we did a big show on stage
and kids narrated everything with puppets
here's the girls up on stage
and our soccer team
I didn't want this to be a sad story
so Lakota, actually
this is her a year ago
and this is her today
in her classroom
and in her uniform
it's what I think every girl and every child deserves
is a home and a safe place to live in
just their most basic, basic needs
Again, 80 million children in the world today that are out of school
that don't have enough food
that aren't safe
some won't make past the age of 5
it's overwhelming and it's sad
I hate to be the bearer of bad news always
and I've to be a lot of the times
but I think we can do it
I think we all have the power to create something
and I don't think you've to go 8,000 miles away
to the foothills of Himalayas
I think the beauty of all of us is that we have talents, we have gifts
and this just happen to remind me I'm really lucky to have found it
and create my little slice of Heaven
my little paradise
and I think that the world'll change when we all found it for ourselves
where we wake up everyday
and we wouldn't rather be anywhere else in the world
doing any other kind of work
and it just so happens it would be great if that work, really, everybody will profited
and only good can come out of it
so that's Kopila Valley to me
it's my slice of heaven
Why do I think it worked? When so many organizations, so many projects tend to fail these days
especially with a foreign aid
I think being young really helped
I'm standing up here at 23 years old not the oldest or the wisest person here
but being young was my greatest strength I think
that attitude that some people call you naive
you know, you think that you're unstoppable
but really if we all had that attitude
that we can do anything, we can be anything
if we follow our dreams in our hearts
and I even see myself sort of losing it as I get older
we start to get more doubtful
we think of all the things we don't have instead of the things we do have
"oh I could do that if I had more money,
I could do that if I had my masters degree,
once I've my PhD,
after I'm settled, after I'm established, after I'm famous
what if every thing you had is everything you've right now
your body and your mind
and that sense of "I can do anything"
I watched my children the other day
I just took this picture
and they were trying to take a kite up in the air
and they were entertaining themselves for 2 hours
just trying to get this kite up
and I was watching them and I was like
"you guys, you're not being able to do it without the wind"
and they just kept trying and trying and trying for hours and hours
and sure enough, just after I came up on the roof
I said "guys you need the wind"
and a huge gust of wind swept trough and the kite went up in the air
and they all just cheered
and I thought of that childlike feeling of
keep going, keep trying and you won't fail
I thought that was a really powerful message for myself
that if we can all go back to that childlike state of
just keep going and have fun with it
it'll be a really beautiful place
so my big do
David yesterday said we've to dream big
so there's 80 million children in the world right now
and in my lifetime
who are orphaned and don't have enough food to eat and are out of primary school
in my lifetime I'd like to see all of them have their basic, most basic human needs met
luckily I'm only 23, so we've a lot of time to do that
and I think that we can
and my little do
I guess would be my 30 children at home waiting for me
a lot of them are under the age of 5 and they need a lot of focus and attention right now
so that's where I'm headed
thank you all very much